Diana Reiss: You may think you're looking
ديانا ريس: ربما تعتقدون بأنكم تنظرون
through a window at a dolphin spinning playfully,
عبر نافذة إلى دلفين يلهو،
but what you're actually looking through
لكن في الحقيقة ما تنظرون من خلاله
is a two-way mirror at a dolphin
هو مرآة بطريقين
looking at itself spinning playfully.
بينما ينظر الدلفين لنفسه وهو يلهو.
This is a dolphin that is self-aware.
هذا دلفين واع بنفسه.
This dolphin has self-awareness.
هذا دلفين يملك وعي ذاتي.
It's a young dolphin named Bayley.
إنه دلفين صغير يدعى بايلي.
I've been very interested in understanding the nature
خلال 30 سنة الماضية كنت جد متحمسة
of the intelligence of dolphins for the past 30 years.
لفهم طبيعة ذكاء الدلفينات.
How do we explore intelligence in this animal
كيف نستكشف ذكاء هذا الحيوان
that's so different from us?
المختلف عنا كثيرا؟
And what I've used is a very simple research tool,
كانت الوسيلة التي استخدمت جد بسيطة،
a mirror, and we've gained great information,
مرآة، وقد توصلنا لمعلومة مدهشة،
reflections of these animal minds.
رد فعل عقل تلك الحيوانات.
Dolphins aren't the only animals, the only non-human animals,
الدلافين ليست الحيوانات الوحيدة أو المخلوقات الغير بشرية الوحيدة،
to show mirror self-recognition.
التي أبدت القدرة على التعرف على نفسها أمام المرآة.
We used to think this was a uniquely human ability,
دائما ما اعتقدنا بأن الإنسان هو الوحيد من يملك تلك القدرة،
but we learned that the great apes, our closest relatives,
لكننا اكتشفنا بأن أقرب المخلوقات إلينا، القردة العليا،
also show this ability.
هي أيضا أبدت تلك القدرة.
Then we showed it in dolphins,
ثم أثبتنا وجودها لدى الدلافين،
and then later in elephants.
وأخيرا لدى الفيلة.
We did this work in my lab with the dolphins and elephants,
قمنا بهذا العمل في مختبري مع الدلافين والفيلة،
Now, it's interesting, because we've embraced
وهذا مثيرللاهتمام، لأننا قد تبنينا
this Darwinian view of a continuity in physical evolution,
التصور الدارويني حول استمرارية التطور الطبيعي،
this physical continuity.
الاستمرارية في التطور الطبيعي.
But we've been much more reticent, much slower
لكننا كنا أكثر ترددا وأكثر بطء
at recognizing this continuity in cognition,
للاعتراف بتلك الاستمرارية في التطور المعرفي
in emotion, in consciousness in other animals.
والشعوري والإدراكي لدى الحيوانات الأخرى.
Other animals are conscious.
الحيوانات الأخرى هي مدركة.
They're emotional. They're aware.
إنها حساسة. إنها واعية.
There have been multitudes of studies with many species
كانت هناك مجموعة من الدراسات التي أجريت على العديد من الحيوانات
over the years that have given us exquisite evidence
لسنوات والتي قدمت لنا براهين مدهشة
for thinking and consciousness in other animals,
عن قدرة التفكير والإدراك لدى الحيوانات الأخرى،
other animals that are quite different than we are in form.
الحيوانات الأخرى جد مختلفة عنا.
We are not alone.
نحن لسنا وحدنا.
We are not alone in these abilities.
لسنا وحدنا من يملك تلك القدرات.
And I hope, and one of my biggest dreams,
وأملي، وواحد من أكبر أحلامي
is that, with our growing awareness
هو، مع تزايد وعينا
about the consciousness of others
بملكة الإدراك لدى الحيوانات الأخرى
and our relationship with the rest of the animal world,
وعلاقتنا مع باقي الحيوانات بالعالم،
that we'll give them the respect and protection
أن نقدم لهم الاحترام والحماية
that they deserve.
التي يستحقونا.
So that's a wish I'm throwing out here for everybody,
وهذه أمنيتي التي أكشفها هنا أمام الجميع،
and I hope I can really engage you in this idea.
وآمل بالفعل، أن أتمكن من جعلكم تنخرطون في تحقيق هذه الفكرة.
Now, I want to return to dolphins,
أود الأن العودة إلى الدلافين،
because these are the animals that I feel like
لأني أحس بأنها الحيوانات التي
I've been working up closely and personal with
عملت معها بشكل وثيق وشخصي
for over 30 years.
لأكثر من 30 سنة.
And these are real personalities.
وهي حيوانات تملك شخصيات حقيقية.
They are not persons, but they're personalities
قد لا تكون أشخاص، لكنها تملك شخصيات
in every sense of the word.
بكل ما تحمله الكلمة من معنى.
And you can't get more alien than the dolphin.
لا يمكنكم العثور على شيء أغرب من الدلفين.
They are very different from us in body form.
فإنهم جد مختلفين عنا جسديا.
They're radically different. They come from a radically different environment.
إنهم مختلفون جذريا. إنهم من بيئة جد مختلفة.
of divergent evolution.
من التطور المختلف.
Look at this body.
انظروا لذلك الجسد.
And in every sense of making a pun here,
وكنوع من اللعب على الكلمات،
these are true non-terrestrials.
إنها حقا فضائية الشكل.
I wondered how we might interface with these animals.
أتساءل كيف قد نتعامل مع تلك الحيوانات.
In the 1980s, I developed an underwater keyboard.
طورت خلال الثمانينات لوحة مفاتيح تحت مائية.
This was a custom-made touch-screen keyboard.
كانت عبارة عن لوحة تعمل باللمس صنعت تحت الطلب.
What I wanted to do was give the dolphins choice and control.
أردت أن أقدم للدلافين إمكانية الاختيار والتحكم.
These are big brains, highly social animals,
إنها حيوانات بأدمغة كبيرة وجد اجتماعية
and I thought, well, if we give them choice and control,
وفكرت أننا إن قدمنا لها إمكانية الاختيار والتحكم،
if they can hit a symbol on this keyboard --
إن كانت قادرة على ضغط الرموز بلوحة المفاتيح --
and by the way, it was interfaced by fiber optic cables
وبالمناسبة، كان اللوح موصول بكابلات ألياف بصرية
from Hewlett-Packard with an Apple II computer.
من هوليت-باكارد مع حاسوب أبل 2.
This seems prehistoric now,
يبدو ذلك من العصور ما قبل التاريخ،
but this was where we were with technology.
لكن كانت تلك هي التكنولوجيا التي نتوفر عليها آنذاك.
So the dolphins could hit a key, a symbol,
كان باستطاعت الدلافين الضغط على مفتاح ما أو رمز
they heard a computer-generated whistle,
فتسمع لصفير يصدر عن الحاسوب
and they got an object or activity.
فتحصل على شيء أو نشاط ما.
Now here's a little video.
وهذا فيديو صغير.
This is Delphi and Pan, and you're going to see Delphi
هؤلاء ديلفي وبان، وستشاهدون ديلفي يضغط على مفتاح،
hitting a key, he hears a computer-generated whistle -- (Whistle) --
فيسمع لصفير يصدر عن الحاسوب --(صفير)--
and gets a ball, so they can actually ask for things they want.
فيحصل على كرة، في الحقيقة بإمكانهما طلب الأشياء التي يحتاجانها.
What was remarkable is, they explored this keyboard
المدهش هو أنهما كانا يستكشفان تلك اللوحة بطريقتهما الخاصة.
on their own. There was no intervention on our part.
فلم يكن هناك تدخل من طرفنا.
They explored the keyboard. They played around with it.
كانا يستكشفان اللوحة. كانا يلهوان بها.
They figured out how it worked.
كانا يحاولان فهم طريقة عملها.
And they started to quickly imitate the sounds
فبدآ بسرعة في تقليد الأصوات
they were hearing on the keyboard.
التي كانا يسمعانها على اللوحة.
They imitated on their own.
كانا يقلدانها بطريقتهما الخاصة.
Beyond that, though, they started learning
وأكثر من ذلك، بدآ تعلم
associations between the symbols, the sounds
الربط بين الرموز والأصوات
and the objects.
والأشياء.
What we saw was self-organized learning,
ما شاهدناه كان عبارة عن التعلم ذو التنظيم الذاتي،
and now I'm imagining, what can we do
وأتخيل اليوم، ما الذي يمكن أن نحققه
with new technologies?
بوجود التكنولوجيا الجديدة.
How can we create interfaces, new windows into
كيف يمكن أن نخلق واجهات ونوافذ جديدة داخل
the minds of animals, with the technologies that exist today?
عقول الحيوانات، بواسطة التكنولوجيا الموجودة اليوم؟
So I was thinking about this, and then, one day,
وبينما كنت أفكر في ذلك في أحد الأيام، إذا بي
I got a call from Peter.
أتلقى اتصالا من بيتر.
Peter Gabriel: I make noises for a living.
بيتر غابرييل: أنا أصنع الأصوات من أجل لقمة العيش.
On a good day, it's music,
وفي أفضل أيامي قد تعتبر تلك موسيقى،
and I want to talk a little bit about
وأرغب في الحديث قليلا عن
the most amazing music-making experience I ever had.
أكثر تجربة عشتها إدهاشا في صتاعة الموسيقى على الإطلاق.
I'm a farm boy. I grew up surrounded by animals,
أنا فتى فلاح. كبرت بين الحيوانات،
and I would look in these eyes and wonder
كنت أنظر إلى عينيها وأتساءل
what was going on there?
ما الذي يحدث بالداخل؟
So as an adult, when I started to read about
وعندما كبرت، بدأت أقرأ حول
the amazing breakthroughs with Penny Patterson and Koko,
الإنجازات المدهشة التي قامت بها بيني باترسون وكوكو،
with Sue Savage-Rumbaugh and Kanzi, Panbanisha,
وسو سافاج-رامبوغ وكانزي وبانبانيشا
Irene Pepperberg, Alex the parrot,
وإيرين بيبربرج واليكس الببغاء،
I got all excited.
كنت جد متحمس.
What was amazing to me also
الأمر الثاني الذي أدهشني
was they seemed a lot more adept
هو أنهم بدوا أكثر براعة
at getting a handle on our language
في فهم لغتنا
than we were on getting a handle on theirs.
منا نحن لفهم لغتهم.
I work with a lot of musicians from around the world,
أنا أعمل مع موسيقيين كثر من جميع أنحاء العالم
and often we don't have any common language at all,
وغالبا ما لا يكون بيننا أي لغة مشتركة،
but we sit down behind our instruments,
لكننا نجلس خلف آلاتنا الموسيقية
and suddenly there's a way for us to connect and emote.
وفجأة، هناك طريقة لنتواصل ونتفاعل.
So I started cold-calling, and eventually got through
لدى بدأت بالقيام باتصالات عديدة تعرفت في نهايتها
to Sue Savage-Rumbaugh,
على سو سافاج-رامبوغ
and she invited me down.
فدعتني لمنزلها.
I went down, and the bonobos
وعندما ذهبت، وجدت أنه كان باستطاعت قردة البابون
had had access to percussion instruments,
العزف على الآلات الإيقاعية
musical toys, but never before to a keyboard.
والألعاب الموسيقية ولكن لم يسبق لها العزف على البيانو.
At first they did what infants do,
في البداية، كانت ردة فعلها كالأطفال،
just bashed it with their fists,
كانت تضربها باليدين عشوائيا،
and then I asked, through Sue,
ثم تساءلت، عن طريق سو،
if Panbanisha could try with one finger only.
إن كان بإمكان بانبانيشا المحاولة بإصبع واحد.
Sue Savage-Rumbaugh: Can you play a grooming song?
سو: هل بإمكانكي عزف أغنية التنظيف؟
I want to hear a grooming song.
أود الاستماع إلى أغنية التنظيف.
Play a real quiet grooming song.
اعزفي أغنية تنظيف هادئة.
PG: So groom was the subject of the piece.
بيتر: كان موضوع القطعة هو التنظيف.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So I'm just behind, jamming,
أنا خلفها، أرتجل،
yeah, this is what we started with.
هذا ما بدأنا به.
Sue's encouraging her to continue a little more.
تشجعها سو للاستمرار بعض الشيء.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
She discovers a note she likes,
تكتشف نغمة أحبتها،
finds the octave.
اكتشفت ديوان.
She'd never sat at a keyboard before.
لم يسبق لها أن جلست أمام بيانو من قبل.
Nice triplets.
نغمات ثلاثية جميلة.
SSR: You did good. That was very good.
سو: أنت تبلين جيدا. كان ذلك رائع.
PG: She hit good.
بيتر: لقد عزفت بشكل جيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So that night, we began to dream,
في تلك الليلة بدأنا نحلم،
and we thought, perhaps the most amazing tool
وفكرنا، أن أروع أدات
that man's created is the Internet,
ابتكرها الإنسان هي الإنترنت،
and what would happen if we could somehow
وما الذي قد يحدث إن نحن تمكنا بشكل ما
find new interfaces,
إيجاد واجهات جديدة،
visual-audio interfaces that would allow
واجهات بصرية-سمعية قد تسمح
these remarkable sentient beings
للتواصل مع تلك الكائنات الرائعة
that we share the planet with access?
التي نتشارك معها الكوكب؟
And Sue Savage-Rumbaugh got excited about that,
وكانت سو سافاج-رامبوغ متحمسة لذلك،
called her friend Steve Woodruff,
اتصلت بصديقها ستيف وودروف،
and we began hustling all sorts of people
وشرعنا بتحريك كل شخص
whose work related or was inspiring,
كان عمله مرتبطا بنا أو ملهما لنا،
which led us to Diana,
وهذا قادنا إلى ديانا،
and led us to Neil.
وإلى نيل.
Neil Gershenfeld: Thanks, Peter. PG: Thank you.
نيل جرشنفلد: شكرا لك، بيتر. بيتر: شكرا لكم.
NG: So Peter approached me.
نيل: اتصل بي بيتر.
I lost it when I saw that clip.
لقد تأثرت عندما رأيت هذا المقطع.
He approached me with a vision of doing these things
لقد اتصل بي مع رؤية حول القيام بهذه الأمور
not for people, for animals.
ليس من أجل البشر بل من أجل الحيوانات.
And then I was struck in the history of the Internet.
لأدهش بعدها من تاريخ الإنترنت.
This is what the Internet looked like when it was born
هذا ما كان يبدو عليه الإنترنت في البداية
and you can call that the Internet
ويمكنكم تسمية هذا بإنترنت
of middle-aged white men,
رجل أبيض في منتصف عمره،
mostly middle-aged white men.
معظم الرجال البيض بمنتصف أعمارهم اليوم.
Vint Cerf: (Laughs)
فينت سيرف: (يضحك)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
NG: Speaking as one.
نيل: وأنا واحد منهم.
Then, when I first came to TED,
وعندما حضرت إلى تيد للمرة الأولى،
which was where I met Peter, I showed this.
حيث التقيت ببيتر، وأريته هذا.
This is a $1 web server,
هذا خادم ويب يساوي دولارا 1،
and at the time that was radical.
شكل ذلك ثورة حينها.
And the possibility of making a web server for a dollar
وتزايدة إمكانية صنع خادم ويب بدولار 1
grew into what became known as the Internet of Things,
لتتحول اليوم لما يعرف بإنترنت الأشياء،
which is literally an industry now with tremendous implications
والذي أصبح اليوم بالفعل صناعة بآثار ضخمة
for health care, energy efficiency.
على الصحة والفعالية الطاقية.
And we were happy with ourselves.
وكنا سعيدين بأنفسنا.
And then when Peter showed me that,
وعندما أراني بيتر هذا،
I realized we had missed something,
أدركت بأننا قد فوتنا أمرا ما،
So we started up this interspecies Internet project.
لدى بدأنا بهذا المشروع عن إنترنت ما بين الأنواع الحية.
Now we started talking with TED
بدأنا الآن بالحديث مع تيد
about how you bring dolphins and great apes and elephants
عن طريقة لإحضار الدلافين والقردة العليا والفيلة
to TED, and we realized that wouldn't work.
إلى تيد، وتبين لنا أن الأمر لن ينجح.
So we're going to bring you to them.
لدى سنذهب بكم إليها.
So if we could switch to the audio from this computer,
إن أمكننا أن نسمع صوت هذا الحاسوب،
we've been video conferencing with cognitive animals,
لدينا اتصال مرئي مع حيونات ذكية،
and we're going to have each of them
وسنتواصل مع كل واحد منهم
just briefly introduce them.
لفترة وجيزة للتعريف عليهم.
And so if we could also have this up, great.
وسيكون من الرائع، إن أمكننا رؤية ذلك على الشاشة فوق.
So the first site we're going to meet
أول موقع سنتواصل معه
is Cameron Park Zoo in Waco, with orangutans.
هو حديقة حيوانات كاميرون بواكو وإنسان الغاب.
In the daytime they live outside. It's nighttime there now.
إنها تمضي النهار خارجا وفي الليل بالداخل.
So can you please go ahead?
هلا تفضلتي بالكلام؟
Terri Cox: Hi, I'm Terri Cox
تيري كوكس: مرحبا، أنا تيري كوكس
with the Cameron Park Zoo in Waco, Texas,
من حديقة حيوانات كاميرون بواكو في تيكساس،
and with me I have KeraJaan and Mei,
ويحضر معي كيراجان ومي،
two of our Bornean orangutans.
اثنين من إنسان الغاب من بورنيو.
During the day, they have a beautiful, large outdoor habitat,
لديهما موئل خارجي جميل، خلال النهار،
and at night, they come into this habitat,
وبالليل، يعودان إلى هنا،
into their night quarters,
إلى موئلهم الداخلي،
where they can have a climate-controlled
حيث يحظيان بمناخ متحكم فيه
and secure environment to sleep in.
وبيئة آمنة للنوم.
We participate in the Apps for Apes program
شاركنا في تطبيقات لبرنامج القرود
Orangutan Outreach, and we use iPads
مع مؤسسة أورنغتان أوتريش، حيث نستخدم أجهزة الأي باد
to help stimulate and enrich the animals,
لتحفيز وتحسين ردود فعل الحيوانات،
and also help raise awareness
وكذا للمساعدة على الرفع من وعي
for these critically endangered animals.
هذه الحيوانات المهددة بالانقراض.
And they share 97 percent of our DNA
إنها تتقاسم معنا 97 بالمائة من حمضنا النووي
and are incredibly intelligent,
وذكية بشكل لا يصدق،
so it's so exciting to think of all the opportunities
لدى من المثير التفكير في كل الفرص
that we have via technology and the Internet
التي بين أيدينا بفضل التكنولوجيا والإنترنت
to really enrich their lives and open up their world.
لتحسين حياتها وفتح عالمها على مصراعيه.
We're really excited about the possibility
ونحن جد متحمسين بخصوص الفرص
of an interspecies Internet,
التي يتيحها إنترنت ما بين الأنواع الحية،
and K.J. has been enjoying the conference very much.
لقد استمتعت كي. جي. كثيرا بالمؤتمر.
NG: That's great. When we were rehearsing last night,
نيل: هذا رائع. عندما كنا نتمرن الليلة الماضية،
he had fun watching the elephants.
كان مستمتع برؤية الفيلة.
Next user group are the dolphins at the National Aquarium.
المستخدم التالي هي الدلافين بالحوض الوطني للأسماك.
Please go ahead.
أرجوا أن تتفضلي.
Allison Ginsburg: Good evening.
أليسون غينسبرغ: مساء الخير.
Well, my name is Allison Ginsburg,
اسمي هو أليسون غينسبرغ،
and we're live in Baltimore at the National Aquarium.
ونحن معكم مباشرة من بالتيمور بالحوض الوطني للأسماك.
Joining me are three of our eight Atlantic bottlenose dolphins:
ويتواجد معي ثلاثة من دلافيننا الثمانية:
20-year-old Chesapeake, who was our first dolphin born here,
هذا تشيزبيك، عمره 20 سنة، وهو أول دلفين ولد هنا،
her four-year-old daughter Bayley,
بايلي ابنته وعمرها 4 سنوات
and her half sister, 11-year-old Maya.
ومايا أخته الغير شقيقة وعمرها 11 سنة.
Now, here at the National Aquarium
نلتزم هنا بالحوض الوطني للأسماك
we are committed to excellence in animal care,
بالجودة في رعاية الحيوانات
to research, and to conservation.
وبالبحث والحماية.
The dolphins are pretty intrigued as to what's going on here tonight.
الدلافين جد مشدودة لما يحدث هنا هذه الليلة
They're not really used to having cameras here
فهي لم تعتد على نواجد الكاميرات هنا
at 8 o'clock at night.
عند الساعة 8 مساء.
In addition, we are very committed to doing
كما أننا ملتزمين بالقيام
different types of research.
بأبحاث متنوعة.
As Diana mentioned, our animals are involved
وكما ذكرت ديانا، فإن حيواناتنا تشارك
in many different research studies.
بالعديد من الأبحاث الدراسية المختلفة.
NG: Those are for you.
نيل: كان ذلك هدية لكم.
Okay, that's great, thank you.
هذا رائع، شكرا لكم.
And the third user group, in Thailand,
المجموعة المستخدمة الثالثة، في تايلاند،
is Think Elephants. Go ahead, Josh.
وهو ثينك إليفنت. تفضل يا جوش.
Josh Plotnik: Hi, my name is Josh Plotnik,
جوش بلوتنيك: مرحبا، اسمي هو جوش بلوتنيك،
and I'm with Think Elephants International,
وأنا أعمل مع ثينك إليفنت انترناشونال،
and we're here in the Golden Triangle of Thailand
ونحن هنا بالمثلث الذهبي التايلندي
with the Golden Triangle Asian Elephant Foundation elephants.
مع مؤسسة المثلث الذهبي للفيل الآسيوي.
And we have 26 elephants here,
ولدينا هنا 26 فيلا،
and our research is focused on the evolution of intelligence with elephants,
وتركز أبحاثنا على تطور الذكاء لدى الفيلة،
but our foundation Think Elephants is focused
ولكن تركز مؤسسة ثينك إليفنت الخاصة بنا
on bringing elephants into classrooms around the world
على إدخال الفيلة الفصول الدراسية حول العالم
virtually like this and showing people
بشكل افتراضي كما نفعل الآن ونظهر للناس
how incredible these animals are.
مدى روعة هذه الحيوانات.
So we're able to bring the camera right up to the elephant,
نستطيع اليوم وضع الكاميرا فوق الفيل،
put food into the elephant's mouth,
ونضع الطعام داخل فمه،
show people what's going on inside their mouths,
ونري للناس ما الذي يجري داخل فمه،
and show everyone around the world
ونظهر لكل واحد حول العالم
how incredible these animals really are.
مدى روعة هذه الحيوانات.
NG: Okay, that's great. Thanks Josh.
نيل: حسنا، هذا رائع، شكرا لكم.
And once again, we've been building great relationships
ومرة أخرى، قمنا ببناء علاقات رائعة
among them just since we've been rehearsing.
بينهم منذ تمرين البارحة فقط.
So at that point, if we can go back to the other computer,
والآن هل يمكننا العودة للحاسوب الثاني،
we were starting to think about how you integrate
بدأنا التفكير في كيفية إدماج
the rest of the biomass of the planet into the Internet,
باقي الكتلة الحيوية للكوكب بالإنترنت،
and we went to the best possible person
وتوجهنا إلى أبرع شخص يمكن
I can think of, which is Vint Cerf,
أن أفكر فيه، وهو فينت سيرف،
who is one of the founders who gave us the Internet. Vint?
وهو أحد المؤسسين الذين قدموا لنا الإنترنت. فينت؟
VC: Thank you, Neil.
فينت سيرف: أشكرك يا نيل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A long time ago in a galaxy — oops, wrong script.
منذ زمن طويل بالمجرة -- آسف، أخطأت في النص.
Forty years ago, Bob Kahn and I
قبل 40 سنة، قمنا بوب كيهن وأنا
did the design of the Internet.
بتصميم الإنترنت.
Thirty years ago, we turned it on.
قبل 30 سنة، قمنا بتشغيله.
Just last year, we turned on the production Internet.
والسنة الماضية، قمنا بتشغيل نسخة الإنتاج من الإنترنت
You've been using the experimental version
لقد استخدمتم طيلة 30 سنة الماضية
for the last 30 years.
نسخة تجريبية.
The production version, it uses IP version 6.
فنسخة الإنتاج تستخدم النسخة 6 من بروتوكول إنترنت "IP".
It has 3.4 times 10 to the 38th possible terminations.
إنه يملك 3.4 ضرب 10 أس 38 نهاية ممكنة.
That's a number only that Congress can appreciate.
وهذا رقم لن يقدر قيمته سوى هذا المؤتمر.
But it leads to what is coming next.
لكنه يقودنا لما هو قادم.
When Bob and I did this design,
عندما قمنا بوب وأنا بهذا التصميم،
we thought we were building a system to connect computers together.
اعتقدنا بأننا كنا نبني نظام يربط الحواسيب ببعضها.
What we very quickly discovered
لنكتشف بعدها مباشرة
is that this was a system for connecting people together.
أنه كان نظام لربط الناس بعضهم ببعض.
And what you've seen tonight
وما تشاهدونه الليلة
tells you that we should not restrict this network
يخبركم بأنه لا يفترض أن نخص هذه الشبكة
to one species,
بنوع واحد،
that these other intelligent, sentient species
بأنه ينبغي أيضا على الأنواع الأخرى الذكية
should be part of the system too.
والمدركة لما حولها أن تكون جزء من النظام.
This is the system as it looks today, by the way.
وبالمناسبة، هذا ما يبدو عليه النظام اليوم.
This is what the Internet looks like to a computer
هذا ما يبدو عليه الإنترنت بالنسبة للحاسوب
that's trying to figure out where the traffic
إنه يحاول معرفة المكان الذي يفترض
is supposed to go.
بحركة الإنترنت التوجه إليه.
This is generated by a program
وقد تم إنشاء ذلك بواسطة برنامج
that's looking at the connectivity of the Internet,
يراقب ارتباطية الإنترنت،
and how all the various networks are connected together.
وكيفية ترابط مختلف الشبكات فيما بينها.
There are about 400,000 networks, interconnected,
هناك حوالي 400,000 شبكة، مترابطة
run independently by 400,000 different operating agencies,
وتعمل بشكل مستقل من خلال 400,000 وكالات تشغيل مختلفة،
and the only reason this works
والسبب الوحيد الذي يجعلها تعمل
is that they all use the same standard TCP/IP protocols.
هو أنها تستخدم جميعا نفس بروتوكول ضبط البث/ بروتوكول الإنترنت الموحد.
Well, you know where this is headed.
وتعرفون إلى أين يأخذنا هذا.
The Internet of Things tell us
يخبرنا إنترنت الأشياء
that a lot of computer-enabled appliances and devices
بأن الكثير من الأجهزة التي تدعم الحاسوب والأجهزة الأخرى
are going to become part of this system too:
ستصبح بدورها جزء من هذا النظام:
appliances that you use around the house,
كالأجهزة التي تستخدمونها بالمنزل،
that you use in your office,
وتلك التي تستخدمونها بمكتبكم،
that you carry around with yourself or in the car.
والتي تحملونها معكم أو بالسيارة.
That's the Internet of Things that's coming.
هذا هو إنترنت الأشياء، إنه قادم.
Now, what's important about what these people are doing
تكمن أهمية ما يقوم به هؤلاء الأشخاص
is that they're beginning to learn
في أنهم بدأوا بتعلم
how to communicate with species
كيفية التواصل مع المخلوقات الأخرى
that are not us
الغير بشرية
but share a common sensory environment.
والتي تشترك معنا في البيئة الحسية المشتركة.
We're beginning to explore what it means
بدأنا نكتشف معنى
to communicate with something
التواصل مع شيء آخر
that isn't just another person.
غير البشر.
Well, you can see what's coming next.
ويمكنكم التكهن بما هو قادم.
All kinds of possible sentient beings
قد يتم ربط كل الأنواع الممكنة
may be interconnected through this system,
من الكائنات الحية بواسطة هذا النظام.
and I can't wait to see these experiments unfold.
ولا أستطيع الإنتظار حتى أرى نتيجة هذه التجارب.
What happens after that?
ما الذي سيحدث بعد ذلك؟
Well, let's see.
دعونا نفكر.
There are machines that need to talk to machines
هناك آلات بحاجة للتحدث لآلات أخرى
and that we need to talk to, and so as time goes on,
والتي نحتاج للحديث إليها نحن أيضا، وبمرور الوقت،
we're going to have to learn
سيكون علينا تعلم
how to communicate with computers
كيفية التواصل مع الحواسيب
and how to get computers to communicate with us
وكيفية جعل الحواسيب تتواصل معنا
in the way that we're accustomed to,
ليس بالطريقة التي اعتدنا عليها،
not with keyboards, not with mice,
من خلال لوحة المفاتيح أو الفأرة،
but with speech and gestures
بل بواسطة الكلام والحركات
and all the natural human language that we're accustomed to.
وباللغة البشرية الطبيعية التي اعتدنا عليها.
So we'll need something like C3PO
سنكون بحاجة لشيء مثل سِّي ثْرِي بِي أُوْ
to become a translator between ourselves
ليكون مترجما لنا
and some of the other machines we live with.
وبعض الآلات الأخرى التي نعيش معها.
Now, there is a project that's underway
هناك مشروع يجري العمل عليه
called the interplanetary Internet.
يدعى إنترنت ما بين الكواكب.
It's in operation between Earth and Mars.
وهو يعمل بين الأرض والمريخ.
It's operating on the International Space Station.
وهو يعمل على متن محطة الفضاء الدولية.
It's part of the spacecraft that's in orbit around the Sun
إنه جزء من المركبة الفضائية الموجودة في مدار الشمس
that's rendezvoused with two planets.
والتي تجمع بين كوكبين.
So the interplanetary system is on its way,
وعليه فإن نظام ما بين الكواكب ماض في طريقه،
but there's a last project,
لكن هناك مشروع آخر،
which the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency,
تقوم به وكالة مشاريع البحوث المتطورة الدفاعية،
which funded the original ARPANET,
التي مولت في الأصل شبكة وكالة مشاريع البحوث المتقدمة،
funded the Internet, funded the interplanetary architecture,
والإنترنت والهندسة ما بين الكواكب،
is now funding a project to design a spacecraft
وهي تمول الآن مشروع لتصميم مركبة فضائية
to get to the nearest star in 100 years' time.
قادرة على بلوغ أقرب نجم إلينا خلال 100 سنة.
What that means is that what we're learning
وهذا يعني بأننا نتعلم
with these interactions with other species
بفضل هذه التفاعلات مع الأنواع الأخرى
will teach us, ultimately,
والتي ستعلمنا في النهاية
how we might interact with an alien from another world.
كيف يمكننا أن نتفاعل مع المخلوقات الفضائية من عالم آخر.
I can hardly wait.
لا يسعني الانتظار.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
June Cohen: So first of all, thank you,
جون كوهين: أولا وقبل كل شيء، شكرا لكم،
and I would like to acknowledge that four people
وأود أن أخبركم بأن هؤلاء الأشخاص الأربعة
who could talk to us for full four days
القادرين على الحديث إلينا خلال 4 أيام كاملة
actually managed to stay to four minutes each,
تمكنوا حقا من اختصار حديثهم في 4 دقائق لكل واحد،
and we thank you for that.
ونحن نشكركم على ذلك.
I have so many questions,
لدي الكثير من الأسئلة،
but maybe a few practical things that the audience might want to know.
لكن قد يرغب الحضور في معرفة بعض الأمور العملية.
JC: Today. This is the first time you're talking about it.
جون:اليوم. هل هذه أول مرة تتحدثون عن هذا الأمر.
Tell me a little bit about where you're going to take the idea.
هلا أخبرتني قليلا حول الكيفية التي ستنفذ بها هذه الفكرة.
PG: I think we want to engage as many people
بيتر: أعتقد بأننا نرغب بإشراك أكبر عدد ممكن
here as possible in helping us
من الأشخاص لمساعدتنا
think of smart interfaces that will make all this possible.
في التفكير بواجهات ذكية تجعل كل هذا ممكنا.
NG: And just mechanically,
نيل جرشنفلد: وبطريقة ميكانيكية فقط،
there's a 501(c)(3) and web infrastructure
لدينا 501 (سي)(3) وبنية تحتية لشبكة الإنترنت
and all of that, but it's not quite ready to turn on,
ورغم هذا، فإنها ما تزال غير قابلة للتطبيق بعد،
so we'll roll that out, and contact us
لدى سنعمل على ذلك، ويمكنكم الاتصال بنا
if you want the information on it.
إن أردتم الحصول على معلومات عن الأمر.
The idea is this will be -- much like the Internet functions
الفكرة هي أن هذا سيكون-- أكثر كوظائف الإنترنت
as a network of networks,
سيكون كشبكة الشبكات،
which is Vint's core contribution,
وهي أساس مساهمة فينت،
this will be a wrapper around all of these initiatives,
والتي ستشكل الغطاء الخارجي لكل هذه المبادرات،
that are wonderful individually, to link them globally.
الرائعة بشكلها الفردي، لربطها على المستوى العالمي.
JC: Right, and do you have a web address
جون: جميل، هل لديكم موقع إلكتروني
that we might look for yet?
يمكننا تصفحه؟
NG: Shortly. JC: Shortly. We will come back to you on that.
نيل: قريبا. جون: قريبا. سنعود إلى هذه النقطة فيما بعد.
And very quickly, just to clarify.
وبشكل سريع، فقط للتوضيح،
Some people might have looked at the video that you showed
قد يفكر بعض الأشخاص الذين شاهدوا الفيديو الذي عرضت
and thought, well, that's just a webcam.
بأنه مجرد اشتخدام عادي للكاميرا.
What's special about it?
ما الشيء الفريد في هذا الأمر؟
If you could talk for just a moment
يمكنك الحديث إن أردت باختصار
about how you want to go past that?
حول كيف ترغب في تجاوز ذلك؟
NG: So this is scalable video infrastructure,
نيل: هذه هي البنية التحتية للفيديو القابل للتحجيم،
not for a few to a few but many to many,
وليس للقليل نحو القليل بل للكثير نحو الكثير،
so that it scales to symmetrical video sharing
إنه معد لتشارك متناظر للفيديو
and content sharing across these sites around the planet.
ولتشارك المحتويات عبر هذه المواقع حول الكوكب.
So there's a lot of back-end signal processing,
هناك العديد من عمليات معالجة الإشارات العكسية،
not for one to many, but for many to many.
ليس لواحد نحو الكثير بل للكثير نحو الكثير.
JC: Right, and then on a practical level,
جون: رائع، وعلى المستوى العملي،
which technologies are you looking at first?
ما هي التكنولوجيات التي ستعملون عليها في البداية؟
I know you mentioned that a keyboard is a really key part of this.
أنا أعلم بأنكم أشرتم إلى أن لوحة المفاتيح هي جزء من الحل لهذا الأمر.
DR: We're trying to develop an interactive touch screen for dolphins.
ديانا ريس: نحن نحاول تطوير شاشة لمس تفاعلية للدلافين.
This is sort of a continuation of some of the earlier work,
ونوعا ما هو استمرار لبعض الأعمال السابقة،
and we just got our first seed money today towards that,
وقد حصلنا اليوم فقط على أول تمويل لنا،
so it's our first project.
لدى فإنه مشروعنا الأول.
JC: Before the talk, even. DR: Yeah.
جون: قبل هذا المؤتمر. ديانا: نعم.
JC: Wow. Well done.
جون: رائع، أحسنتم.
All right, well thank you all so much for joining us.
حسنا، شكرا لكم جميعا لانضمامكم إلينا.
It's such a delight to have you on the stage.
إنها لمتعة أن تكونوا معنا على المسرح.
DR: Thank you. VC: Thank you.
ديانا: شكرا لكم. فينت: شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)